<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Clippings on 学习笔记</title><link>https://erisehe.github.io/notebook/tags/clippings/</link><description>Recent content in Clippings on 学习笔记</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://erisehe.github.io/notebook/tags/clippings/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The extimate core of understanding: absolute metaphors, psychosis and large language models - AI &amp; SOCIETY</title><link>https://erisehe.github.io/notebook/notes/Clippings/Psychoanalysis/The-extimate-core-of-understanding-absolute-metaphors-psychosis-and-large-language-models-AI-SOCIETY/</link><pubDate>Fri, 17 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://erisehe.github.io/notebook/notes/Clippings/Psychoanalysis/The-extimate-core-of-understanding-absolute-metaphors-psychosis-and-large-language-models-AI-SOCIETY/</guid><description>&lt;p>Advertisement&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-extimate-core-of-understanding-absolute-metaphors-psychosis-and-large-language-models">
 The extimate core of understanding: absolute metaphors, psychosis and large language models
 &lt;a class="anchor" href="#the-extimate-core-of-understanding-absolute-metaphors-psychosis-and-large-language-models">#&lt;/a>
&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Main Paper&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
 &lt;a href="https://www.springernature.com/gp/open-science/about/the-fundamentals-of-open-access-and-open-research">Open access&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Published:&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Volume 40, pages 1265–1276, (2025)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
 &lt;a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/?utm_source=chatgpt.com#citeas">Cite this article&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>You have full access to this 
 &lt;a href="https://www.springernature.com/gp/open-science/about/the-fundamentals-of-open-access-and-open-research">open access&lt;/a> article&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
 &lt;a href="https://link.springer.com/journal/146">
 &lt;img src="https://media.springernature.com/w72/springer-static/cover-hires/journal/146?as=webp" alt="" /> AI &amp;amp; SOCIETY&lt;/a> 
 &lt;a href="https://link.springer.com/journal/146/aims-and-scope">Aims and scope&lt;/a> 
 &lt;a href="https://submission.springernature.com/new-submission/146/3">Submit manuscript&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="abstract">
 Abstract
 &lt;a class="anchor" href="#abstract">#&lt;/a>
&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This paper delves into the striking parallels between the linguistic patterns of Large Language Models (LLMs) and the concepts of psychosis in Lacanian psychoanalysis. Lacanian theory, with its focus on the formal and logical underpinnings of psychosis, provides a compelling lens to juxtapose human cognition and AI mechanisms. LLMs, such as GPT-4, appear to replicate the intricate metaphorical and metonymical frameworks inherent in human language. Although grounded in mathematical logic and probabilistic analysis, the outputs of LLMs echo the nuanced linguistic associations found in metaphor and metonymy, suggesting a mirroring of human linguistic structures. A pivotal point in this discourse is the exploration of “absolute metaphors”—core gaps in reasoning discernible in both AI models and human thought processes and central to the Lacanian conceptualization of psychosis. Despite the traditional divide between AI research and continental philosophy, this analysis embarks on an innovative journey, utilizing Lacanian philosophy to unravel the logic of AI, using concepts established in the continental discourse on logic, rather than the analytical tradition.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>(PDF) Circling the Void: Using Heidegger and Lacan to think about Large Language Models</title><link>https://erisehe.github.io/notebook/notes/Clippings/Psychoanalysis/PDF-Circling-the-Void-Using-Heidegger-and-Lacan-to-think-about-Large-Language-Models/</link><pubDate>Mon, 05 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://erisehe.github.io/notebook/notes/Clippings/Psychoanalysis/PDF-Circling-the-Void-Using-Heidegger-and-Lacan-to-think-about-Large-Language-Models/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="abstract">
 Abstract
 &lt;a class="anchor" href="#abstract">#&lt;/a>
&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The paper aims to unite two currently distinct ways of thinking about and working with language. Large language models and continental philosophy, especially Martin Heidegger&amp;rsquo;s thinking about language and, building on Sigmund Freud, Jacques Lacan&amp;rsquo;s structural psychoanalysis. We show that the concept of language that Heidegger, Freud, and Lacan discussed and utilized in clinical frameworks is quite well matched by modern LLMs. This allows us to discuss a problem of negation and negativity that is central to continental discourse but absent from current LLM research. This also means that we offer a radically different approach than is usual in the philosophy of artificial intelligence, since we base our concepts on thinkers who are often neglected in the discourse of analytic philosophy that is closer to AI research. To this end, we also indicate where the ontological differences of the proposed approach lie. Our aim, however, is to address both AI researchers and continental philosophers.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Algorithmic unconscious: why psychoanalysis helps in understanding AI - Humanities and Social Sciences Communications</title><link>https://erisehe.github.io/notebook/notes/Clippings/Psychoanalysis/Algorithmic-unconscious-why-psychoanalysis-helps-in-understanding-AI-Humanities-and-Social-Sciences-Communications/</link><pubDate>Thu, 23 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://erisehe.github.io/notebook/notes/Clippings/Psychoanalysis/Algorithmic-unconscious-why-psychoanalysis-helps-in-understanding-AI-Humanities-and-Social-Sciences-Communications/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="abstract">
 Abstract
 &lt;a class="anchor" href="#abstract">#&lt;/a>
&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The central hypothesis of this paper is that the concepts and methods of psychoanalysis can be applied to the study of AI and human/AI interaction. The paper connects three research fields: machine behavior approach, psychoanalysis and anthropology of science. In the “Machine behavior: research perspectives” section, I argue that the behavior of AI systems cannot be studied only in a logical-mathematical or engineering perspective. We need to study AI systems not merely as engineering artifacts, but as a class of social actors with particular behavioral patterns and ecology. Hence, AI behavior cannot be fully understood without human and social sciences. In the “Why an unconscious for AI? What this paper is about” section, I give some clarifications about the aims of the paper. In the “Unconscious and technology. Lacan and Latour” section, I introduce the central thesis. I propose a re-interpretation of Lacan’s psychoanalysis through Latour’s anthropology of sciences. The aim of this re-interpretation is to show that the concept of unconscious is not so far from technique and technology. In the “The difficulty of being an AI” section, I argue that AI is a new stage in the human identification process, namely, a new development of the unconscious identification. After the imaginary and symbolic registers, AI is the third register of identification. Therefore, AI extends the movement that is at work in the Lacanian interpretation of the mirror stage and Oedipus complex and which Latour’s reading helps us to clarify. From this point of view, I describe an AI system as a set of three contrasting forces: the human desire for identification, logic and machinery. In the “Miscomputation and information” section, I show how this interpretative model improves our understanding of AI.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>