<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>BERTopic on 学习笔记</title><link>http://localhost:1317/tags/BERTopic/</link><description>Recent content in BERTopic on 学习笔记</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="http://localhost:1317/tags/BERTopic/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>FinTextSim: Enhancing Financial Text Analysis with BERTopic</title><link>http://localhost:1317/notes/Clippings/LLM/FinTextSim-Enhancing-Financial-Text-Analysis-with-BERTopic/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://localhost:1317/notes/Clippings/LLM/FinTextSim-Enhancing-Financial-Text-Analysis-with-BERTopic/</guid><description>&lt;p>arXiv:2504.15683v1 [cs.CL] 22 Apr 2025&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Simon Jehnen Javier Villalba-Díez Joaquín Ordieres-Meré&lt;/p>
&lt;h6 id="abstract">
 Abstract
 &lt;a class="anchor" href="#abstract">#&lt;/a>
&lt;/h6>
&lt;p>Recent advancements in information availability and computational capabilities have transformed the analysis of annual reports, integrating traditional financial metrics with insights from textual data. To extract valuable insights from this wealth of textual data, automated review processes, such as topic modeling, are crucial. This study examines the effectiveness of BERTopic, a state-of-the-art topic model relying on contextual embeddings, for analyzing Item 7 and Item 7A of 10-K filings from S&amp;amp;P 500 companies (2016–2022). Moreover, we introduce FinTextSim, a finetuned sentence-transformer model optimized for clustering and semantic search in financial contexts. Compared to all-MiniLM-L6-v2, the most widely used sentence-transformer, FinTextSim increases intratopic similarity by 81% and reduces intertopic similarity by 100%, significantly enhancing organizational clarity. We assess BERTopic’s performance using embeddings from both FinTextSim and all-MiniLM-L6-v2. Our findings reveal that BERTopic only forms clear and distinct economic topic clusters when paired with FinTextSim’s embeddings. Without FinTextSim, BERTopic struggles with misclassification and overlapping topics. Thus, FinTextSim is pivotal for advancing financial text analysis. FinTextSim’s enhanced contextual embeddings, tailored for the financial domain, elevate the quality of future research and financial information. This improved quality of financial information will enable stakeholders to gain a competitive advantage, streamlining resource allocation and decision-making processes. Moreover, the improved insights have the potential to leverage business valuation and stock price prediction models.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>